in this video we're going to talk about
how to
simplify rational expressions when
adding or subtracting them whenever they
have like denominators
so let's start with this example 3x over
plus
four x plus seven over five
because these two fractions share the
same denominator
we can combine it as a single fraction
so we can write it as three x
plus four x plus seven
all divided by the common denominator
which is five
three x plus four x is seven x
and if we want to we can take out the
gcf which is seven
leaving behind x plus one
so that's the final answer for this
example
let's try another one
7 over x
minus 11 over x
so we can combine it as a single
fraction
seven minus eleven over x
and seven minus eleven is negative four
so the answer is going to be negative
four divided by x
try this one
seven x plus four
divided by x plus two
plus five x
minus seven over x plus two
so let's write it as a single fraction
seven x
plus five x i'm gonna put the like terms
together
plus four minus seven
all divided by x plus two
seven x plus five x is twelve x
four minus seven is negative three
so we can take out a three if we want so
it's going to be four x
minus one over x plus two
and so that's it
let's try one more example
three x minus ten
divided by
x minus one
minus
five x minus twelve
over x minus one
now be careful with this one go ahead
and try it
so first let's write it as a single
fraction
so it's going to be three x minus ten
now this negative sign applies to the 5x
and
negative 12.
so initially i'm going to write it using
parentheses
before you combine like terms distribute
the negative sign
so it's going to be 3x minus 10
minus 5x
plus 12.
3x minus 5x is negative 2x
negative 10 plus 12
is positive 2.
now let's take out the gcf which is
negative two negative two x divided by
negative two
that's positive x
and positive two divided by negative two
is negative one
so notice that we can cancel x minus one
which means the final answer
is simply minus two